Planetary systems outside our own
الأنظمة الكوكبية خارج نظامنا
are like distant cities whose lights we can see twinkling,
مثل المدن المتباعدة التي يمكننا رؤية تلألؤ أضوائها،
but whose streets we can't walk.
لكن لا يمكننا المشي في شوارعها.
By studying those twinkling lights though,
لكن بدراسة تلألؤات الضوء تلك،
we can learn about how stars and planets interact
يمكننا فهم كيف تتفاعل النجوم والكواكب
to form their own ecosystem
لتشكل أنظمتها الحيوية الخاصة
and make habitats that are amenable to life.
وإنشاء بيئات مناسبة للحياة.
In this image of the Tokyo skyline,
في هذه الصورة لأفق طوكيو،
I've hidden data
قد أخفيت بيانات
from the newest planet-hunting space telescope on the block,
من أحدث تلسكوب فضائي للتفتيش عن الكواكب قريب منا،
the Kepler Mission.
بعثة كيبلر.
Can you see it?
هل بإمكانكم رؤيتها؟
There we go.
ها هي ذا.
This is just a tiny part of the sky the Kepler stares at,
هذا فقط جزء صغير من السماء التي يحدق فيها كيبلر،
where it searches for planets
حيث يبحث عن كواكب
by measuring the light from over 150,000 stars,
من خلال قياس ضوء أكثر من 150,000 نجم،
all at once, every half hour,
دفعة واحدة، كل نصف ساعة،
and very precisely.
وبكل دقة.
And what we're looking for
وما نبحث عنه
is the tiny dimming of light
هو تعتيمات بالغة الصغر للضوء
that is caused by a planet passing in front of one of these stars
يسببها مرور الكوكب أمام إحدى هذه النجوم
and blocking some of that starlight from getting to us.
وحجب بعض ضوء النجوم من الوصول إلينا.
In just over two years of operations,
وفقط خلال سنتين من الإشتغال،
we've found over 1,200
وجدنا أكثر من 1,200
potential new planetary systems around other stars.
أنظمة كوكبية محتملة جديدة حول نجوم أخرى.
To give you some perspective,
ولإعطائكم نظرة شاملة،
in the previous two decades of searching,
خلال عقدي البحث الأخيرين،
we had only known about 400
تعرفنا فقط على 400
prior to Kepler.
قبل كيبلر.
When we see these little dips in the light,
حين نرى هذه الإنخفاضات الصغيرة للضوء،
we can determine a number of things.
نستطيع تحديد عدد من الأشياء.
For one thing, we can determine that there's a planet there,
شيء واحد هو أنه يمكننا أن نحدد أن هناك كوكبا هناك،
but also how big that planet is
لكن كذلك مدى ضخامة ذلك الكوكب
and how far it is away from its parent star.
ومدى بعده عن النجم الأم.
That distance is really important
المسافة هي في غاية الأهمية
because it tells us
لأنها تخبرنا عن
how much light the planet receives overall.
مقدار الضوء الذي يستقبله الكوكب إجمالا.
And that distance and knowing that amount of light is important
وتلك المسافة ومعرفة مقدار الضوء ذاك مهم،
because it's a little like you or I sitting around a campfire:
لأنه يشبه نوعا ما جلوسي أو جلوسك حول نار المخيم.
You want to be close enough to the campfire so that you're warm,
تريد أن تكون قريبا بما فيه الكفاية للنار حتى تتدفأ،
but not so close
لكن ليس قريبا جدا
that you're too toasty and you get burned.
بحيث تتحمص وتحترق.
However, there's more to know about your parent star
على كل حال، هناك أمور أكثر لمعرفتها حول النجم الأم
than just how much light you receive overall.
من فقط مقدار الضوء الذي تستقبله إجمالا.
And I'll tell you why.
وسأريكم لماذا.
This is our star. This is our Sun.
هذا نجمنا. هذه شمسنا.
It's shown here in visible light.
معروض هنا بالضوء المرئي.
That's the light that you can see with your own human eyes.
وهو الضوء الذي يمكننا رؤيته بأعيننا البشرية.
You'll notice that it looks pretty much
ستلاحظون أنه يبدو إلى حد كبير
like the iconic yellow ball --
مثل الكرة الصفراء الشهيرة --
that Sun that we all draw when we're children.
تلك الشمس التي رسمناها جميعا حين كنا صغارا.
But you'll notice something else,
لكنكم ستلاحظون أمرا آخر،
and that's that the face of the Sun
وهو أن هناك على وجه الشمس
has freckles.
نمشا.
These freckles are called sunspots,
هذا النمش يسمى بقعا شمسية،
and they are just one of the manifestations
وهي فقط إحدى مظاهر
of the Sun's magnetic field.
الحقل المغناطيسي للشمس.
They also cause the light from the star to vary.
وهي كذلك تجعل الضوء القادم من النجوم يتغير.
And we can measure this
ويمكننا قياس هذا
very, very precisely with Kepler and trace their effects.
في غاية الدقة باستخدام كيبلر وتتبع آثاره.
However, these are just the tip of the iceberg.
مع ذلك، هذه ليست سوى قمة الجبل الجليدي.
If we had UV eyes or X-ray eyes,
إن كنا نتوفر على أعين ترا الأشعة الفوق بنفسجية أو أشعة X،
we would really see
يمكننا أن نرى حقا
the dynamic and dramatic effects
الآثار الديناميكية والدراماتيكية
of our Sun's magnetic activity --
لأنشطة شمسنا المغناطيسية --
the kind of thing that happens on other stars as well.
نفس الأنشطة التي تحصل في نجوم أخرى كذلك.
Just think, even when it's cloudy outside,
فقط فكروا، حتى إن كان الجو مضببا خارجا،
these kind of events are happening
هذا النوع من الأحداث يحصل
in the sky above you all the time.
في السماء فوقنا طوال الوقت.
So when we want to learn whether a planet is habitable,
وبالتالي حين نريد أن نعرف ما إذا كان كوكب صالحا للسكن،
whether it might be amenable to life,
ما إذا كان مناسبا للحياة،
we want to know not only how much total light it receives
نريد أن نعرف ليس فقط مقدار الضوء الذي يستقبله
and how warm it is,
ومدى دفئه،
but we want to know about its space weather --
لكن نريد أن نعرف جو فضائه --
this high-energy radiation,
هذه الإشعاعات ذات الطاقة العالية،
the UV and the X-rays
الأشعة الفوق بنفسجية وأشعة X
that are created by its star
التي ينتجها نجمه
and that bathe it in this bath of high-energy radiation.
والتي يغمرها في حمام الإشعاعات العالية الطاقة هذا.
And so, we can't really look
وهكذا، لا يمكننا فعلا أن ننظر
at planets around other stars
إلى كواكب حول نجوم أخرى
in the same kind of detail
بنفس مقدار التفصيل
that we can look at planets in our own solar system.
الذي ننظر به إلى الكواكب في نظامنا الشمسي.
I'm showing here Venus, Earth and Mars --
هنا أعرض الزهرة والأرض والمريخ --
three planets in our own solar system that are roughly the same size,
3 كواكب في نظامنا الشمسي والتي لها تقريبا نفس الحجم،
but only one of which
لكن فقط واحد منها
is really a good place to live.
هو مكان مناسب فعلا للحياة.
But what we can do in the meantime
لكن ما يمكننا القيام به في الوقت الحالي
is measure the light from our stars
هو قياس الضوء من نجومنا
and learn about this relationship
وفهم هذه العلاقة
between the planets and their parent stars
بين الكواكب والنجم الأم
to suss out clues
للتحقق الدقيق من القرائة
about which planets might be good places
حول أي الكواكب قد تكون أماكن جيدة
to look for life in the universe.
للبحث عن حياة في الكون.
Kepler won't find a planet
كيبلر لن يجد كوكبا
around every single star it looks at.
حول كل نجم ينظر إليه.
But really, every measurement it makes
لكن في الواقع، كل قياس يجريه
is precious,
ثمين،
because it's teaching us about the relationship
لأنه يخبرنا عن العلاقة
between stars and planets,
بين النجوم والكواكب،
and how it's really the starlight
وكيف أن ضوء النجم هو في الواقع
that sets the stage
ما يهيئ المحيط المناسب
for the formation of life in the universe.
لتشكل الحياة في الكون
While it's Kepler the telescope, the instrument that stares,
في حين أن تلسكوب كيبلر والأجهزة هي التي تحدق،
it's we, life, who are searching.
إنه نحن، الحياة، من يبحث.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)